hey push students let's cover everything
you need for period
8 before we start print out the free
speed review sheet to help you follow
along with this video it's free and you
can find the link in the description
below right now look at period 8 Circle
any people event vocabs think that you
might not quite remember that you know
you need to focus on as we were youw
once you're confident that you've
mastered a topic you can check it off
and move on to the next all right here
we go following World War II America
experienced significant economic growth
the GI Bill gave veterans the
opportunity to receive a college
education and buy a home this
contributed to the baby boo and the rise
of the sunb Bel region and Eisenhower's
Interstate Highway Act connected the
country improved trade and travel and
made road trips a popular Pas
neighborhoods like lown represented the
American dream for many families by
offering affordable mass-produced homes
in the suburbs also the television
brought families together around the
small screen shaping popular culture by
influencing fashion music and even
politics this all contributed to a
growing culture of Conformity for
American families however teams rebelled
against this by listening to rock and
roll music while the beach wrote novels
like the affluent society to criticize
these social norms following World War
II tensions between the United States
and the Soviet Union led to a cold war
America joined both the United Nations
and NATO officially abandoning its
policy of isolationism in an effort to
combat communism America adopted a
policy of containment which was
recommended by George Kennan in his Long
Telegram early examples of containment
include the Truman Doctrine which
successfully repelled communism in
grease in turkey and the Marshal plan
which provided financial aid to help
rebuild War torn Western Europe
containment was also seen in proxy wars
like the Korean War where the United
States and the Soviet Union indirectly
engaged in Warfare even though it ended
an an arous and Korea remain divided it
was seen as an early success of
containment during his two terms
President Eisenhower built upon Truman's
Cold War policies his Eisenhower
Doctrine pledged military aid to Middle
Eastern countries that were threatened
by communism he was also more willing to
threaten the use of military force
including nuclear weapons to achieve
foreign policy objectives this was known
as break menhip but upon leaving office
he warned of the dangers of the growing
military industrial complex that
occurred during his presiden at the end
of the Korean War Cuba fell to Communism
making it a hot spot for the Cold War
due to its close proximity to America
the Kennedy administration oversaw the
failed B pigs incident I brought the US
and the Soviet Union to the break of
nuclear war during the Cuban Missile
Crisis the Cold War played a large role
in American culture during this time
period too fears overc communism led to
the second Red Scare Americans built
nuclear fallout shelters and children
practiced duck cover drills and senator
Joseph McCarthy led a series of witch
hunts against accuse Communists in the
government and the Army America also
heavily invested in defense Industries
and space research to keep up with the
Soviets in the arms and space races
there was also a renewed push for civil
rights in the 1950s as African-Americans
fought for equality and an end to racial
segregation the land Mark Supreme Court
case browny the Board of Education
declared segregation in schools
unconstitutional a huge victory for the
movement integration however was met
with Fierce resistance for example the
Little Rock N9 faced hostility the
National Guard was sent in when they
tried to integrate Little Rock Central
High School peaceful resistance and
Civil Disobedience were the main methods
for Fighting For Change Rosa Parks led
the way when she refused to give a
proceed on the bus sparking the
Montgomery Bus Boycott also Martin
Luther King Jr was a key figure in the
Civil Rights Movement advocating for
non-violent protest in his letter from a
Birmingham Jail and by delivering his
iconic I Have a Dream speech I have a
dream that one day yes this nation will
rise
up and live out the true meaning of its
Creed the Greensboro sens were another
form of peaceful protest where
African-American students sat at a
White's only Lunch Counter demanding
equal treatment but not everybody agreed
with the strategies of the movement
Malcolm X and groups like the Black
Panthers advocated for black empowerment
and self-defense the movement achieved
several legislative victories the Civil
Rights Act of 1964 was a huge milestone
that outlawed discrimination Bas of race
color religion sex and national origin
and following the horrors that were
shown on television like Bloody Sunday
the Voting Rights Act of 1965 was passed
and the 24th amendment outlawed po taxes
as the fight for civil rights carried on
at home a fight for democracy was
happening in Vietnam President
Eisenhower warned of a domino theory in
Asia are doing that if Vietnam were to
fall to Communism others might as well
tensions of Vietnam continued to
escalate under President Kennedy he
tried to limit American involvement but
America officially got involved in the
war following an alleged attack on the
US Navy by the North Vietnamese in
response Congress passed the Gul toning
resolution which gave Johnson the green
light to use military force in Vietnam
within a few years America had over
500,000 troops in Vietnam a draft
lottery was also instituted fueling
protest of resistance from the
counterculture movement especially on
college campuses the Vietnam War was
America's first televised War showing
live coverage of events like the 1968
Ted offensive the surprise attack on the
American and South Vietnamese forces was
a turning point in public opinion
because it shook confidence in the war
effort news of the brutal melee Massacre
also fueled anti-war sentiments and the
release of the Pentagon papers in 1971
confirmed Americans concerns proving
they had been lied to about the state of
the war especially by the Johnson
Administration Nixon was elected in 1968
in part because he supported a policy
Club Vietnamization when he became
president he gradually began withdraw
American troops in 1973 Nixon declared
the US had achieved Peace With Honor
with the signing of the Paris Accords
which ended the war in Vietnam it's also
important to know President Johnson's
domestic agenda because it's been all
over the exam LBJ expressed in his
inaugural address that he was going to
wage a war on poverty and he was able to
get significant legislation passed to
help some of America's most vulnerable
groups this included Healthcare reforms
such as Medicare and Medicaid he also
signed the elementary and secondary
Education Act and created the Department
of Housing and Urban Development his
vast reforms became known as the Great
Society this was the most expansive
social welfare legislation passed since
FDR's New Deal some especially
conservatives opposed these new policies
arguing that they increase government
spending and bordered on socialism
Nixon's foreign policy was based on
Dayton he and his secretary of state
Henry kisser H to deescalate Cold War
tension he did this through the
Strategic arms limitations treaty which
was the first time in the Cold War where
both sides agreed to limit their nuclear
arsenals and by visiting China he
reopened lines of communication and
trade the Arab Israeli War also took
place during Nixon's presidency as a
result of supporting Israel OPEC nations
placed an embargo on the United States
the Embargo caused oil prices to
Skyrocket long lines at gas stations and
an economic recession but Nixon's second
term was overshadowed by the Watergate
scandal the Scandal involved the illegal
Breakin of the Democratic National
Committee headquarters by members of
Nixon's Administration after being
caught trying to cover up the Scandal
Nixon chose to resigned before being
impeached he remains the only President
to resign from office I shall resign the
presidency effective that at noon
tomorrow Nixon's Vice President Gerald
Ford took office following his
resignation one of his first actions as
president was to pardon Nixon which
angered some Americans who wanted the
president brought to Justice also during
his ter Vietnam saw the fall of Saigon
which was a huge victory for communism
and Ford battled poor economic
conditions including continued inflation
despite his whip inflation now campaign
the economy did not recover Ford lost
his bid for re-election in 1976 to Jimmy
Carter Carter also only served one term
as president his term was plagued by
Rising inflation high unemployment and
continued oil shortages however was
praised for his role in the Camp David
Accords a political agreement between
Egypt and Israel but he was criticized
for his handling of the Iranian hostage
crisis after 52 Americans were taken
hostage in the US Embassy in tran
President Carter failed to negotiate a
release of the captives this combined
with his Malay speech contributed to the
victory of Ronald Reagan in the election
of 1980 during the 1960s and 1970s a
modern environmentalist movement also
emerged the movement was inspired by
Rachel Carson's Silent Spring which shed
light on the harmful effects of
pesticides on the environment and
Wildlife this led to increased awareness
about the need to protect the
environment and pav the way for
important environmental regulations like
the Clean Air Act and the Clean Water
Act in 1970 the Environmental Protection
Agency was also created a huge victory
for the movement and Earth was created
in 1970 as well to raise awareness for
environmental issues and promote
sustainability students were utilized to
support this cause just like they were
in the movement against the Vietnam War
the successes of the African-American
civil rights movement inspired other
groups to challenge societal norms and
demand equality the Feminine Mystique by
Betty freden sparked a wave of feminism
groups like The National Organization of
Women advocated for gender equality and
push for the Equal Rights Amendment but
the ra never passed in part because of a
backlash from conservatives lgbtq plus
rights also gain momentum with activists
demanding an end to discrimination based
on sexual orientation or gender identity
the 1969 Stone War riots were seen as a
pivotal moment in the fight for rights
for the lgbtq plus Community there was
also a movement for Latino rights Cesar
Chavez the founder of the national Farm
Workers Association advocated for Farm
Workers rights and fair treatment for
Latinos in the United States this
coincided with the chano movement which
advocated for political and social
rights for Mexican am and the American
Indian movement fought for the rights of
indigenous people pushing for the
recognition of their sovereignty and
advocating for cultural preservation
they were most well known for their
year-long occupation of alcatra Island
so what does this look like on exam day
for causation you can see questions
about the effects of the Cold War for
comparison you want to be able to
compare the tactics of various civil
rights leaders from Martin Luther King
Jr to Malcolm X or you could be asked to
compare the similarities and differences
between the Cold War policies of each of
the presidents and for change in
continuity you most likely ask how
American foreign policy changed after
World War II remember after World War II
America finally abandoned its long-held
tradition of isol ation ISM check out
the aush ultimate review packet for more
help we've got timeline study guides and
Essay practice follow the link in the
description below for a free preview and
if you think this video is helpful like
And subscribe thanks for
[Music]
watching